Guide to the Rose Cumming, Russell L. Cecil, and Affiliated Families Photographs and Papers 1870s-2012 PR 393
New-York Historical Society
- Series I. Cumming family photographs and papers, 1870s-2012
  - Sub-series I.D. Other Cumming and related families, 1870s-1943
    - Hughes and Fennell family photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Marjorie (Hughes) Loney. Newspaper clipping and photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Frederick R. Loney Jr. photographs, personal (oversize), undated (Box 10 (flat), Folder 5)
- Series II. Cecil family photographs and papers, 1872-2003
  Series II is organized in four sub-series. Material within each sub-series is sorted alphabetically by document type or topic.
  Sub-series II.A. Russell LaFayette Cecil, 1880s-1975
  Sub-series II.B. Eileen Cumming Cecil, 1890s-1982
  Sub-series II.C. Russell Cumming Cecil, 1920s-2003
  Sub-series II.D. Other Cecil and related families, 1872-1986
  - Sub-series II.A. Russell La Fayette Cecil, 1880s-1975
    Sub-series II.A includes some magazine profiles and memorial tributes recounting the contributions of Dr. Russell LaFayette Cecil (1881–1965) to the field of rheumatology, but the accompanying letters, photographs, newspaper clippings, Princeton University memorabilia, and other material is of a familial, non-professional nature. (See Sub-series II.C for correspondence between Dr. Cecil's grandson and an author studying the former's Textbook of Medicine.) Three folders hold apparently unpublished autobiographical material, and a diary chronicles his golf scores between 1950 and 1963.
    - Article about: "Textbook Titan," MD Medical Newsmagazine, vol. 2, no. 3, 1958 March (Box 3, Folder 36)
      Profile pp. 78-79.
    - Article about: "Focus on Dr. Russell L. Cecil," Image, vol. 4, no. 2, 1962 June (Box 10 (flat), Folder 6)
      Profile pp. 21-24.
    - Article about: "In Dedication to Russell L. Cecil, M.D.," Arthritis and Rheumatism: Official Journal of the American Rheumatism Association, vol. 6, no. 4, part II, 1963 August (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Entire issue dedicated to Dr. Cecil.
    - Article about: Obituary, Time, 1965 June 11 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      Brief obituary, p. 92.
    - Article about: (eulogy) "Russell LaFayette Cecil, 1881-1965" (6 copies), [1965 June 4] (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Article about: (tribute) "Russell Lafayette Cecil, 1881-1965" (4 copies) (Box 3, Folder 40)
      Biographical pamphlet issued by McNeil Pharmaceutical.
    - Article about: "Men of Medicine: 'You Must Do Everything With Love',", undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Article by: "Studies on Pneumococcus Immunity," reprinted from The Journal of Experimental Medicine, vol. 38, no. 2, 1923 August 1 (Box 3, Folder 42)
      With Edward Mott Wolley's "Robbing Pneumonia of Its Terrors," Good Housekeeping, November 1923.
    - Article by: "Present Status of Arthritis," Modern Medicine, vol. 24, no. 19 (2 copies), 1956 October 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Article by: "The Editing of a Modern Medical Textbook," International Record of Medicine, vol. 169, no. 11, whole number 2885, 1956 November (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Autobiography (3 folders), undated (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
    - Baby hair, [1880s] (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Blueprints, Cecil residence, 153-155 East 61st Street, 1950 January 20 (Box 13 (flat), Folder 1)
    - Calling cards, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Cards stamped "Doctor Russell L. Cecil" in Tiffany & Co. box.
    - Cecil family genealogical material (2 folders), 1870s-1965 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
      Includes a family tree drawn by the processing archivist, Joseph Ditta, and added to the collection for user reference (2019).
    - Diary (personal), 1908 April 2 - May 2 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Diary (golf), 1927-28, 1950-63 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Diary (travel), 1931 Summer (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Diary (engagements), 1960 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Ephemera, circa 1930s-1959 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Letters, 1898-1900 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Letters, 1905-1910, 1912, 1917-1918 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Letters, 1923-1950 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Letters, etc., 1951-1971 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Letters (undated) (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Letters of condolence to widow, Eileen Cumming Cecil, 1965 June-October (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Letters of condolence to son, Russell Cumming Cecil, 1965 June-July (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Motion picture film, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
      "Pop's Senate Hearing Film / Dr. Russell L. Cecil."
      Restricted
      Until this film has been preservation formatted, it may not be played. In any case, N-YHS lacks the required playback equipment.
    - Newspaper and periodical clippings, 1938-1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Newspapers (facsimiles), [1854, 1861-1864] (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Reprints [?] of the [London] Times (1854 October 9, November 13); New York Herald (1861 February 11, April 20); New York Tribune; (1861 April 15); Daily Richmond Examiner (1862 June 3); [Richmond] Daily Dispatch (1863 October 20); and Charleston Daily Courier (1864 September 26).
    - Photographs, personal, circa 1891-1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, personal (oversize), [1900s-1940s] (Box 10 (flat), Folder 7)
    - Photographs (slides), travel, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
      "Cecil trips to Egypt, Italy, Greece."
    - Poetry, 1923, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      Poems composed for his wife, Eileen Cumming Cecil (1923) and granddaughter, Sarah Cecil (1964).
    - Princeton University, Class of 1902 armband [?] (Box 5, Folder 5)
      Orange felt armband with black "02."
    - Princeton University, Class of 1902 photograph, 25th anniversary, [1927] (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Princeton University, Class of 1902, Septennial Record of the Class of Nineteen Hundred and Two, 1910 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      Russell L. Cecil entry p. 31.
    - Princeton University, Class of 1902, Twenty-Fifth Year Record of the Class of 1902, Princeton University, 1902-1927 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Russell L. Cecil entry pp. 64-65.
    - Princeton University, sheet music, "Old Nassau", 1905 (Box 10 (flat), Folder 8)
    - Scrapbook, circa 1923-1974 (Box 7, Enclosure 1 (folder 3))
    - Scrapbook (loose pages), circa 1951-1963 (Box 10 (flat), Folder 9)
  - Sub-series II.B. Eileen Cumming Cecil, 1890s-1982
    Sub-series II.B includes photographs, passports, scrapbooks, scattered letters and cards, and other material relating to Eileen Cumming Cecil (1892–1982). Of note are the tear sheets of interior decorating articles she wrote in the 1920s for House Beautiful and Vogue, and a miniature 1927 pamphlet entitled "The Place of the Fashion Magazine," which reprints the text of a lecture that she, a "practical fashionist," delivered for the Department of Fine Arts of New York University. A scrapbook gathers Florsheim Shoes advertisements publicized by her firm, Eileen Cumming Associates.
    - Address books (2), 1960s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Article by: "The Place of the Fashion Magazine", 1927 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Article by: "Summer in the Dining Room," Charm, 1924 July (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Articles by: House Beautiful, 1920s (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Articles by: Vogue, 1920s (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Audiotape: "Mrs. Cecil", undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
      Until this tape has been preservation formatted, it may not be played. In any case, N-YHS lacks the required playback equipment.
    - Audiotape: unidentified, [1961?] (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Certificate of citizenship, 1932 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Cumming family tree, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 17)
      Includes notes by Sarah Cumming Cecil (donor) and a family tree drawn by the processing archivist, Joseph Ditta, and added to the collection for user reference (2019).
    - Ephemera, etc., 1923-1964 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Financial, 1966-1978 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Letters and cards, 1913-1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Letters of condolence to son, Russell Cumming Cecil, 1982 September-October (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Marriage certificate, license, invitations, 1923 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Newspaper clippings, general, 1937-1970, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Newspaper clippings, personal, 1923-1982 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Odlum Award, 1965 October 7 (Box 5, Folder 25)
      Eileen Cumming Cecil was corecipient of the 1965 Floyd B. Odlum Award presented by the New York Chapter of the Arthritis Foundation, Inc. She served on the organization's board of governors.
    - Passports, 1925, 1932, 1968, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Photograph album, 1920s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Photograph album (fragment), undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Photographs, miscellaneous, 1920s-circa 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, personal, circa 1890s-1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Photographs, personal (framed), circa 1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, personal (oversize), [1890s] (Box 11 (flat), Folder 2)
    - Photographs (negatives), undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Postcards, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Menu, 1937 June 26 (Box 11 (flat), Folder 1)
      Dinner menu, Compagnie Generale Transatlantique French Line.
    - Scrapbook, 1880s-circa 1965 (Box 7, Enclosure 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1890s-1950s (Box 11 (flat), Folder 3)
    - Scrapbook, 1890s-1970s (Box 11 (flat), Folder 4)
    - Scrapbook, Eileen Cumming Associates, Florsheim Shoes advertisements, [1930s?] (Box 11 (flat), Folder 5)
  - Sub-series II.C. Russell Cumming Cecil, 1920s-2003
    Sub-series II.C includes personal material—letters, photographs, and a few youthful school essays—of architect and historic preservationist Russell Cumming Cecil (1926–2009). The sole item regarding his work is a December 1972 House & Garden profile of a house he designed for Wilfred Cohen on Long Island Sound. Also included is a folder of correspondence between Russell C. Cecil's son, Dr. Russell N. A. Cecil, an orthopedic surgeon, and Dr. James A. Pitman Jr., a distinguished professor at the University of Alabama who was (in 1999) preparing a paper on textbooks of internal medicine and, naturally, sought to include information on Dr. Russell L. Cecil's 1927 Textbook of Medicine.
    - Cecil-Cumming cemetery plot, 1958-1992, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Childhood drawings, 1936, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Wilfred Cohen House clippings, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Diary (fragment), [?] January 1-20 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Insurance Appraisal Property of Nancy and Russell Cecil, 1986 September (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Letters, etc., 1926-2003, undated (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Newspaper clippings (family), 1894-1986 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Photograph album, childhood, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Photographs (loose), circa 1927-1951 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Photographs, personal (oversize), 1920s-1930s (Box 11 (flat), Folder 6)
    - St. Paul's School, 1941, 2010, undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
      Includes an obituary for Russell Cumming Cecil in Alumni Horae, vol. 90, no. 2 (Winter 2010), 41.
    - Yale University, 1945-1946 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Russell N. A. Cecil correspondence re: grandfather, Dr. Russell L. Cecil, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Sub-series II.D. Other Cecil and related families, 1872-1986
    Sub-series II.D includes letters, photographs, newspaper clippings, and other material relating to the relatives of Russell LaFayette Cecil: his parents, the Presbyterian minister Rev. Russell Cecil (1853–1925) and Alma (Miller) Cecil (1858–1948); brothers John Howe Cecil Sr. (1883–1939) and James McCosh Cecil (1891–1954); sisters Alma (Cecil) Cary (1885–1932) and Elizabeth (Cecil) Scott (1900–1948); nieces Patricia Cecil Hass (1928– ) and Amanda (Cecil) Schuster; and nephews John Howe Cecil Jr. and James M. Cecil Jr.
    - Alma (Cecil) Cary and family. Photographs, 1910, 1942, undated (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Alma (Miller) Cecil. Letters, etc., 1924-1944, undated (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Alma (Miller) Cecil. Photographs, 1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - James M. Cecil Sr. Photograph, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - James M. Cecil Jr. and family. Newspaper clippings and photographs, 1960s, 1986, undated (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - John Howe Cecil Sr. Letters, 1899-1900 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - John Howe Cecil Jr. Calling card, undated (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Rev. Russell Cecil. Memorials, [1925] (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Rev. Russell Cecil. Miscellaneous, 1872-1954 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Rev. Russell Cecil. Photographs, undated (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Russell Howe Cecil. Photograph, undated (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Patricia Cecil Hass. Swampfire (New York: Dodd, Mead & Company), 1973 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Amanda (Cecil) Schuster. Newspaper clippings and photographs, 1938-1942 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Elizabeth (Cecil) Scott and family. Letter and photographs, 1935, undated (Box 6, Folder 31)